Preliminary Guide to the Archibald S. Foord Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Archibald Smith Foord papers
1926-1968
MS 136
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.5
Correspondence, manuscripts, teaching materials, research notes, speeches, printed matter, and a small amount of family correspondence comprise the papers of Archibald Foord. Nearly half the papers consist of note cards, research materials and manuscripts, primarily on British history. Included is the complete manuscript of: His Majesty's Opposition, 1714-1830 (published in 1964). Another large segment of the papers reflects Foord's teaching career at Yale and includes class notes, examinations, lectures, student papers, and grade books. Some family correspondence for the years 1934-1945 is also in the papers.
Foord, Archibald S.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Andrew Keogh, 1953; of the Dean's Office of Saybrook College, 1969; and of Archibald S. Foord's estate, 1970.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 2, materials concerning Yale students, is restricted until January 1, 2032 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Biographical / Historical
Archibald S. Foord: professor of history at Yale University, 1940-1942, 1946-1969; served in the U.S. Navy, 1942-1946; author of numerous books and articles.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, manuscripts, teaching materials, research notes, speeches, printed matter, and a small amount of family correspondence comprise the papers of Archibald Foord. Nearly half the papers consist of note cards, research materials and manuscripts, primarily on British history. Included is the complete manuscript of: His Majesty's Opposition, 1714-1830 (published in 1964). Another large segment of the papers reflects Foord's teaching career at Yale and includes class notes, examinations, lectures, student papers, and grade books. Some family correspondence for the years 1934-1945 is also in the papers.
Great Britain -- History -- 1714-1837; Educators; Historians; Blum, John Morton, 1921-2011; Foord, Archibald S.; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; May, Georges, 1920-; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History
- Inventory
  - Manuscripts and correspondence, 1926-1968 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence, 1934-1945 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, exams, notes (Box 1)
  - Materials concerning Yale students
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials concerning Yale students are closed until January 1, 2032 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - Yale student records (Box 2)
    - Grade books, 1940-1941, 1946-1949, 1951-1957 (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning student advisees (Box 2)
  - His Majesty's Opposition
    - Manuscript (Box 3)
    - Page proofs (Box 3)
    - Charts and notes (Box 3)
  - Maps (Box 4)
  - War deports (Box 4)
  - Military records, 1945-1955 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript submitted to Clarendon Press (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 1952-1967 (Box 5)
  - Class notes and exams, 1940-1963 (Box 5)
  - Lecture notes, 1956-1959 (Box 6)
  - Class papers dealing with historical subjects, 1934-1940 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 6)
  - Historical notes (Box 7)
  - Historical note cards (Box 8)
  - Historical note cards (Box 9)